Okay בוקר טוב *boker
tov*, today's דף *daf* is ק''יח *kuf yud chet*, 118. We're on
the, I guess I would say, pen-penultimate דף
*daf*, the third-to-last דף *daf* of the מסכת *masechet*, and we're continuing
to discuss the history of when things could be brought on the
במות bamos *bamot* at various stages in Jewish history and what could
be brought and so on. So we worked through a debate of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, first of all on the private
במה bamah. *bama*, whether it was limited to an עולה olah *olah*
and שלמים shlamim. *shelamim*, or did it even include מנחה minchah *mincha*,
something that wasn't a sacrifice, how do you deal with an issue
of like נזיר *nazir*, which in the end we wound up saying
that even though we're talking about even the עולה olah *olah* of
a נזיר *nazir*, and the question was does the fact that it
becomes obligated through a free-will vow pull into the obligatory category? But
that fundamentally it's עולה olah *olah* and שלמים shlamim. *shelamim* and maybe
even not all of those, not the obligatory ones.
That's that. And then in the public במה גדולה bamah gedolah. *bama
gedola* in גלגל Gilgal, *Gilgal*, the ציבור tzibur *tzibur* could bring everything,
and the question is what could the individual bring? Could he bring
even private, could he bring there everything? So the public one really
functioned very similar to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* or
to שילה Shilo *Shilo*, right? The only difference would be whether private
במות bamos *bamot* are allowed. But in the public במה bamah. *bama*,
then the individual could really bring whatever he wanted, right? So that
was the position of, whose position was that? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda*. That was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*'s position. רבי
יהודה Yehudah, *Rabbi Yehuda* basically said everything. So for him, that was
very permissive. It basically meant if you're going to go to the
public central במה bamah. *bama*, then everything, everything can be brought. And
in addition, we're allowing you to bring your עולה olah *olah* and
your שלמים *shelamim* on your rooftop. That was רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*.
Whereas the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
said: no, in this period where we're letting you do your private
stuff on your rooftop, then when you come to the public you're
still limited in the same way. You want to operate as a
free agent, as everybody doing their own private one, that's limited to
this sense of free will, it doesn't include obligatory sacrifices because you're
basically doing it as this sense of to worship freely wherever you
want, so therefore even when you come here, you're not going to
get to plug into that obligatory sort of structure. So even when
you come to the central one, you can only bring an עולה
*olah* and a שלמים *shelamim*, although it is true that the ציבור
tzibur *tzibur*, the community,
does all of the normal sacrifices. So that was the debate about
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* against רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and חכמים Chachamim
*Chachamim*, whether the individual is able to bring everything in the central
public במה bamah. *bama* or can they there also only bring an
עולה *olah* and a שלמים *shelamim*. And we pointed out that according
to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim*, you have
a strange situation that for the entire duration when you had like
the גלגל Gilgal *Gilgal* and נוב Nov *Nov* and גבעון Giv'on. *Givon*
and so on, nobody could bring a חטאת chatas, *chatas* to atone
for sin, and not only that, nobody could bring if you had
certain types of טומאה *tumah*, you couldn't bring a חטאת chatas. *chatas*
to achieve purity and to cleanse yourself. And you wouldn't be able
to eat קרבנות korbanos. *korbanos*. So here everybody is bringing all their
קרבנות korbanos, *korbanos* on their private rooftop and then there's this whole
class of people that aren't able to eat the קרבן פסח korban
Pesach. *Korban Pesach* and aren't able to eat any of the קרבנות
korbanos *korbanos* that are being brought during the year because they can't
bring this חטאת chatas, *chatas* and they can't purify themselves from the
טומאה *tumah* of יולדת *yoledes* or זב *zav* or זבה *zava* or
whatever. So that's the very strange reality. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*'s approach
is much more expansive and permissive. Now one thing that I should
say that I failed to say yesterday and David mentioned is what
is the difference? Why was it that in a place like גלגל
Gilgal, *Gilgal* and נוב Nov *Nov* and גבעון Giv'on *Givon*, if there
was a central public במה bamah. *bama*, and there was a single
central public במה bamah *bama*, why wasn't it considered like שילה Shilo
*Shilo*? Why were the במות bamot *bamot* still permissible? What made its
status different than that of שילה Shilo *Shilo*? And the answer is
that in those places they did not have the ארון Aron *aron*
there. The ארון aron *aron* had been taken and we're going to
discuss that briefly about
how certainly the ארון Aron *aron* was sort of taken captive by
the פלשתים Plishtim, *Plishtim* and whatever, that's certainly in the נוב Nov
*Nov* and גבעון Giv'on, *Givon* status and so on. Okay, so because
of the lack of all having the entire setup in it, it
makes sense. If there's no ארון Aron *aron*, if you think about
it,
if there's no
ארון Aron *aron*, then it's not a central place of God's presence,
right? So it's just like me making a במה bamah. *bama* on
a rooftop. So the only difference, it's not really a משכן mishkan
*Mishkan*, it's not really the place of God's presence. So then it's
really just, and this is the phrase the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses,
like a במה קטנה bamah ktana. *bama ketana* or a במה גדולה
bamah gedolah *bama gedola*, right? But fundamentally this place, גלגל Gilgal *Gilgal*,
is no longer like where God is present in any more particular
place, it's just the central במה bamah. *bama*, the במה bamah. *bama*
that we're all as a community we're all going to have. public
worship here. But it’s not really, so if it’s not really that
place of God’s presence, it’s not a משכן, mishkan, it’s a במה
גדולה. bamah gedolah Right? So that’s really the difference as opposed to
like שילה Shilo, and the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash there really you
had the ארון Aron. and the sense of God's presence, and that's
why, you know, that came with the איסור במות issur bamos elsewhere.
Because if God is fundamentally present in one place, it—it טאקע taka
makes a lot of sense, it's just all clicking for me now.
If God is fundamentally present in one place, then you don't have
a right to be worshipping elsewhere, right? If that sense of God's
experienced presence, whatever that means, is more, is fundamentally in one place.
So that's why it has an איסור במות. issur bamos. When you
don't have the sort of the presence of the שכינה Shechinah in
a place like גלגל, Gilgal, so if God isn't more present in
גלגל Gilgal than God is anywhere else, we—you should be able to
worship everywhere, right? So in that case, it's really everywhere God is
equally present and everywhere you can offer on a במה. bamah. There's
just like a במה גדולה bamah gedolah. and a במה קטנה. bamah
ketanah, Okay, so as opposed to, you know, in שילה Shilo and
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, where we speak about that sense of God's
presence, so that entails then the fundamental sense of the איסור issur
of במות bamot elsewhere. Okay, so that's sort of the basic structure.
Alright, so now we continue with this sense of within גלגל, Gilgal.
right? We said again there's this debate. רבי יהודה says that everybody
can do everything normal, that the only difference of גלגל Gilgal, and
let's say שילה Shilo is whether private במות bamot are permissible. But
in גלגל, Gilgal. the ציבור tzibur. did everything and the יחיד yachid
could do everything he or she wanted either, with all of the
normal קרבנות. korbanos Whereas רבי מאיר and the חכמים say no, even
the יחיד, yachid, the יחיד yachid was restricted even in גלגל Gilgal
to עולה ושלמים. olah ushlamim. And now we're going to move on
to the position of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who restricts even the
ציבור tzibur in a place like גלגל. Gilgal. So let's take a
look on ק״ח עמוד א׳ Kuf Chet amud aleph about eight lines
down. אמר מר רבי שמעון אומר. Amar mar, Rabbi Shimon omer. So
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says even in גלגל, Gilgal, you could only
bring the פסח Pesach and fixed קרבנות, korbanos. even the ציבור. tzibur
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mai ta’ama deRabbi Shimon? What's the reason of
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? דכתיב, Dechtiv, the verse says: ויעשו בני ישראל
את הפסח בגלגל. Vaya’asu venei Yisrael es haPesach beGilgal. There you go,
they made the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach? So how does that prove
only the קרבן פסח? korban Pesach. פשיטא, Peshita, because the answer is
it's obvious. What, of course they're going to bring the קרבן פסח.
korban Pesach? Now, of course, I mean, okay, maybe it might be
obvious that they're going to do it, but, you know,
the פסוקים pesukim want to tell a story. So but whatever, that's
the question. Maybe why emphasize בגלגל? beGilgal? We know they're in גלגל.
Gilgal I don't know. Anyway, isn't that obvious that you bring a
קרבן פסח? korban Pesach. So אלא הא קמשמע לן, Ella ha kamashma
lan, this is what it teaches us: דחובות כעין פסח הוא דקרב
הלא כעין פסח לא קרב. Dechovos ke’ein Pesach hu dekarav hala ke’ein
Pesach lo karav.
That really even in—since the time of היתר במות, heter bamos, even
גלגל Gilgal? is not much different than your private במה. bamah And
it's not like fundamentally the ציבור tzibur can bring all the קרבנות
korbanot. in גלגל. Gilgal, Even in גלגל, Gilgal, there's only going to
be a few small exceptions of what can be done in גלגל
Gilgal, that can't be done in a private במה. bamah But it's
not fundamentally different than a private במה. bamah. So what are the
things that can be done in גלגל? Gilgal Well, a קרבן פסח.
korban Pesach Now, why is that an exception? You could say it's
an exception because obviously that is the central ציבור tzibur. קרבן, korban,
that is the central foundational, you know, annual experience of reconnecting to
the narrative and all of that and a sense of membership in
the people. So of course we want to allow that, number one.
And number two, you know, the פסח Pesach to some degree is
like a—it still has a quasi-nature of a private קרבן. korban. Each
individual brings it. It's fundamentally like a שלמים. So פסח Pesach is
one thing we allow. But again, the basic operating concept here for
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you know, is that even in גלגל, Gilgal,
it's not much different than a private במה. bamah. So number one
that and number two, fixed obligations. Well, fixed obligations certainly seems to
broaden it significantly. So let's talk about that, okay? So now the
גמרא Gemara. says like this:
הלא כעין פסח לא קרב, Hala ke’ein Pesach lo karav, but it
has to be like פסח. Pesach. So like פסח Pesach is a
fixed obligation. ואידך, Ve’idach, and the חכמים that say no, you can
pretty much do every—the ציבור tzibur can do everything in גלגל, Gilgal?
מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוחנן. Mibe’ei lei lechiderabbi Yochanan. They need it for
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's teaching. דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי בן
נזיר ערל מקבל הזיה. De’amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yose ben Nazir
arel mekabbel hazayah. That even an ערל arel can be sprinkled the
ashes of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Okay, which is interesting. Why
not? Because there's an idea that the ערלות, arlus, the foreskin, is
like a corpse. And when somebody separates from an ערל, arel, the
whole issue of בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, it's
like they—you know, can somebody who had a ברית מילה bris milah
a day before קרבן פסח korban Pesach? bring a קרבן פסח? korban
Pesach, There was a position that you needed to go through a
whole period of the sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה אדומה,
Parah Adumah, like a seven-day purification process after separating—after having a ברית
מילה, bris milah, that it was like separating off from a corpse
and so
on, which it very much does, I guess, you know, the way
it becomes like a sign of non-Jewish
identity and something very foreign, obviously, etc., etc. So with that in
mind that there was that attitude, the question was: let's say we're
not going to פסקן pasken that you need a whole— 7-day purification
process when you've cut off your ערלה *orla*.
But can you, if we do still have some of that sense
about what that ערלה *orla* is about, like association with a corpse,
can we sprinkle on you the ashes of פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah*
and can you go through a purification process of טומאת מת *tumas
meis* while you are also an ערל *arel*? Okay, you got the
question? Does that get in the way of you purifying yourself from
טומאת מת *tumas meis*? So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says it does
not. And how does רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* know this? He knows
this from the story of the first קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*, because
if you remember the story of the first קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*
says what did they do first thing before they brought the קרבן
פסח *korban Pesach*? They did a ברית מילה *bris milah*. So based
on the chronology in the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*, right where they cross
the ירדן Yarden *Yarden* on the 10th of ניסן *Nisan* and then
he said they needed a day to recover, so he said the
earliest they could have done the ברית מילה *bris milah* was on
the 11th. Now, if you cannot do sprinkling of the פרה אדומה
*Parah Adumah* when you have the ערלה *orla* on you, so that
would mean everybody there who had been in the מדבר midbar? *Midbar*
was טמא מת *tamei meis*, right? Because everybody had been dying for
40 years. Okay, so if everybody was טמא מת *tamei meis*, you
go to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*, you need to get
you a purification process. Well, if the ברית מילה *bris milah* happens
on day 11,
okay, okay, and then you have 12, 13, 14, right? And then
15, right? And then this is where you're going to bring the
קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*, right?
So where did they sprinkling the ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah
Adumah* in order to be able to be טהור *tahor* for the
קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*? So the earliest time, so you have to
wait three days, right? You start doing it, you do it day
3 and day 7. So if you couldn't do it when there
was an ערלה *orla*, right, then the earliest, the earliest
you
could do it is after the ברית מילה *bris milah* on day
11, you could do day 3 of the ashes, okay, right? You'd
have to start counting back here because obviously they became טמא *tamei*
earlier, and this would have been day 3. Then this would have
been 4, 5, 6, so then the final day 7 of the
ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* could have only been on
the 15th of ניסן *Nisan*, which would have been too late, which
means you couldn't have eaten the קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*. So the
fact that they ate the קרבן פסח *korban Pesach* means they must
have been able to sprinkle the ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah
Adumah* on day 10, and they must have been able to sprinkle
the ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* even when somebody was
an ערל *arel*. Okay, so that's רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*'s point that
even an ערל *arel* can have the ashes of פרה אדומה *Parah
Adumah* sprinkled on him, and that's what the תורה *Torah* is teaching
us why it emphasizes that they made the first פסח *Pesach*. It's
so funny. Maybe it just wants to tell us the very fascinating
story, like of all the stories in יהושע Yehoshua. *Yehoshua*, this was
probably the one that you remember one of the most, one of
the first ones. But no, it has to be telling us a
הלכה halacha *halacha* point. So either it's telling us that what you
could do in גלגל *Gilgal* was very limited, only קרבן פסח *korban
Pesach* and things like it, or it's telling you this הלכה *halacha*
about that the ashes of the פרה אדומה *Parah Adumah* can even
be when somebody is an ערל *arel*. Okay, so now
the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this, תני תנא tana. קמיה דרב אדא
בר אהבה *Tani tana kamei d'Rav Ada bar Ahava*, אין בין במה
גדולה bamah gedolah, לבמה קטנה אלא פסח וחובות שקבוע להם זמן *Ein
bein bamah gedolah l'bamah ketanah ela pesach v'chovos shekavua lahem zman*. So
this is
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*'s position. It's really fundamentally like a
במה קטנה bamah ketanah. *bamah ketanah* except you're allowed קרבן פסח *korban
Pesach* and you're allowed fixed time קרבן *korban*. Now, I'll read the
parentheses because some take it out, but because it does get to
the theme that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to be bothered
with about this idea, אמר ליה amar lei, *Amar lei*, so he
said back to him, ואי בעית אימא eima *v'ee baisaimo*, יחיד yachid
חובות שקבוע להם זמן מנא ליה *yachid chovos shekavua lahem zman minalei*?
Where does an individual bring fixed obligations? Now the question is, what
do you mean? Of course, we're not talking about an individual, we're
talking about the ציבור tzibur *tzibur* in the במה bamah. גדולה *bamah
gedolah*. But the point is that this approach the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
understands is fundamentally saying that a במה bamah. גדולה *bamah gedolah* is
really not much different than a במה קטנה bamah ketanah. *bamah ketanah*,
and there's a certain a little bit extra allowance, but fundamentally it's
the same קרבנות korbanot *korbanos*. So קרבן פסח *korban Pesach* as we
said, even for
יחיד yachid *yachid*.
No, even for the ציבור tzibur, *tzibur*, because if even for the
ציבור tzibur *tzibur* you're going to have this very narrow limiting, then
that means conceptually we're thinking about it, right? If he's saying אין
בין במה קטנה bamah ketanah. לבמה גדולה *ein bein bamah ketanah l'bamah
gedolah*, right, until now, what do you mean אין בין *ein bein*,
fundamentally the במה bamah, גדולה *bamah gedolah* was a completely different operation,
it was the ציבור tzibur *tzibur*, it was all the קרבנות korbanot
*korbanos* etc. This is starting with the base of במה קטנה bamah
ketanah. *bamah ketanah* and a little bit expanding it. So therefore the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is understanding that it has to be built off
of what you can do in a במה bamah. קטנה *bamah ketanah*.
So קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*, number one you could just say well
that's got to be an exception anyway, but number two as I
said, individuals do bring it, it's a type of a שלמים *shelamim*,
fine. But if you say that you bring fixed obligations, well if
you say you're going to bring an עולה *olah*, I'm just giving
you the answer like the עולת תמיד olat tamid, *olat tamid*, fine.
So you bring an עולה *olah* on your private במה bamah. *bamah*
and you can bring a ציבור *tzibur* obligatory עולה *olah* on a
public, but you're still fundamentally bringing an עולה *olah*. olah. But if
you’re going to say you bring like the fixed, the חטאת, chatas,
every רגל regel there was a חטאת, chatas right? יום כיפור Yom
Kippur there was a חטאת. chatas If you say you bring the
fixed obligations that include a חטאת, chatas, then it’s categorically different than
a במה קטנה, and it’s not fundamentally an expansion of a במה
קטנה. So that’s what bothers the גמרא. Gemara So אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said back to him, אסימיה? asimei? So should I, should
I eliminate this position? Does this not make any sense? Because it
seems to be too expansive if it’s fundamentally based on a במה
קטנה. אמר ליה, he said back to him, no,
תתרגמי מתניתין בעולת חובה דאיכא עולת נדבה. titargemi matnitin be'olat chovah de'ika
olat nedavah. No, no, no. This position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
would say an obligatory עולה gets done in the במה גדולה because
that’s built off of the free-will עולה that gets done on the
במה קטנה. So the עולת תמיד, olat tamid. the two daily sacrifices,
would get brought. On the מוספין, musafin, right, the עולה part of
the מוספין musafin would get brought, but not the חטאת, chatas okay,
not the חטאת chatas. of the רגל, regel, not the חטאת chatas
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that would not get brought.
אי חטאת יחיד הוא חובת קביעה לזמן מי איכא? ei chatas yachid
hu chovat kvi'ah lizman mi ika? Because if it were a חטאת,
chatas, okay, and we’re going to say we don’t have a private
חטאת chatas, on the personal במה that we should do the parallel
for it in the public במה. So the גמרא Gemara says ולוקמה
במנחת חובה דאיכא חביתין? velukma beminchat chovah de'ika chavitin? Okay, but there’s
another thing you could bring in this public במה. You could bring
the daily מנחה minchah of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because, you
know, or not only that, because, you know, you would have, you
could bring a
private מנחה minchah in your personal במה. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, קסבר אין מנחה בבמה. kasavar ein minchah bevama. Even, no, there’s
the position that there’s not a מנחה in a במה. So therefore
the only thing you’re going to bring according to רבי שמעון—again, Rabbi
Shimon it’s funny what exactly made the גמרא Gemara say this, it
isn’t exactly in the words of רבי שמעון—but Rabbi Shimon you understand
conceptually. Since רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said a public במה is only
more than the private במה the following ways, he’s understanding fundamentally for
him it’s conceptually really a private במה. Really it follows the model
of a private במה. Okay, but it’s for the ציבור. It’s a
little bit bigger. But we’re really building off of a private במה.
So therefore what you’re going to do there has to be seen
as building off of the private במה. He still says חובה, chovah,
it should be a חטאת.
What? חטאת is a חובה chovah and it’s part of...
no, but that’s the גמרא's Gemara rereading it. The גמרא Gemara understands
that since his model is based on expanding what’s done in a
private במה, but it’s fundamentally within that structure, even when he says
the obligatory fixed sacrifices, he only means the עולות. olot. He only
means things that have a counterpart on a private במה. So קרבן
פסח, either we need to have it—so that’s an exception—or it’s still
fundamentally private and it’s a type of a שלמים. And a fixed
ציבור עולה you would bring, but a fixed חטאת, that you would
not bring. Okay, that’s how the גמרא Gemara understands his model. But
again, what’s really interesting about all of this, as we said, is,
right, that because this is not like the place of the ארון
Aron and the משכן mishkan, and so on, it’s being called not
like a משכן, Mishkan. right? It’s being called a במה גדולה. And
you really see that in רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. that really has
it operating very similar to a במה קטנה. Okay, like, you know.
But so that’s where we are. But according to the חכמים, it
could be that the ציבור could bring everything and maybe even for
רבי יהודה the יחיד yachid. could bring everything. But nevertheless, since it
isn’t this משכן, Mishkan. right, it’s only this במה גדולה, that still
allows it to be private במה.
So basically what we're seeing is some opinions that say there’s no
difference between a יחיד yachid. and a ציבור, potentially, which is רבי
יהודה.
Yeah,
all the way to רבי שמעון. Right, that says there’s no difference
between the ציבור and the יחיד. Right, that even the ציבור is
not much more than the יחיד. That is correct. But you know,
that might be like in terms of the conceptual model. In practice,
it still meant a lot. It meant that every day you’re bringing
the עולת תמיד. It means you’re bringing the מוסף musaf on שבת,
Shabbos, the מוספין musafin on the רגלים, regalim, right? Not with the
חטאת, but still there’s a lot of public, you know, regular worship
that creates a basic structure. But like let’s say יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. התוספות Tosafot discusses that you wouldn’t have the basic עבודה avodah
of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That’s a pretty big thing not to
be doing. On the other hand, to the degree that that is
all based on a מקדש Mikdash model, if you think about it,
right, it’s cleansing the מקדש, Mikdash, you know, and it’s cleansing the
place where God’s שכינה shechinah is, and that has to be
cleansed when you go into the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, right? So
there it makes a certain amount of like sense that, right, that
you’re not going—that that’s not appropriate for like a place like גלגל,
which doesn’t have that place of like the שכינה’s shechinah presence. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: באו לשילה. ba'u leShilo.
Now we’re moving off of גלגל going to שילה, Shilo and שילה
Shilo... is where they had the first quasi בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash.
okay? So מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? And there the במות
bamos were forbidden, and שילה Shilo? operated essentially like a בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash The only way it operated different—is it didn’t operate different—but
once שילה Shilo was destroyed, the במות bamos became permissible again. And
once the מקדש Mikdash was destroyed, the במות did not become permissible
again. Okay,
so מנא הני מילי, mena hanei milei, where’s this from? אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן כתוב אחד אומר. amar Rabbi Chiyya
bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan katuv echad omer. So a verse saying
where do you know this idea that in שילה... Shilo Base was
out of like of like, you know, brick and the top was
you know was or whatever stone and the top was a
what do you call it a curt not a curtain what's the
word יריעה. yeri'ah.
Yeah but this curtain usually you talk about like this right not
a horizontal anyway whatever it is you know was a cloth covering
like they had in the משכן. Mishkan Where do you know that
was the structure in שילה? Shilo מנא הני מילי. Mina hani mili.
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar
Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, כתוב אחד אומר, Kasuv echad omer, one verse
says ותביאהו בית השם שילה, Vatevi'ehu Beis Hashem Shilo, the house a
בית bayis which has a sense of like you know you know
stone. וכתוב אחד אומר, Vekasuv echad omer, the other says ויטוש משכן
שילה, Vayitosh Mishkan Shilo, God abandoned the משכן. Mishkan משכן Mishkan is
like the משכן Mishkan they had in the במדבר bamidbar in the
wilderness right the tabernacle the tent like structure. Okay. אהל שכן באדם,
Ohel shiken ba'adam, the אהל ohel and there it says explicitly the
אהל ohel the tent that God caused to dwell amongst humans. Okay
so what is it? Is it a house or is it a
tent? וכתיב Uksiv and it says וימאס באהל יוסף Vayimas be'ohel Yosef
and when God abandoned שילה Shilo? he despised the אהל יוסף ohel
Yosef ובשבט אפרים לא בחר. uveshevet Ephrayim lo vachar. Okay so is
it an אהל ohel or is it a בית? bayis? הכיצד? Hakeitzad?
How do you reconcile this? לא היתה שם תקרה אלא אבנים מלמטה
ויריעות מלמעלה. Lo haysa sham tikra ela avanim milmata viyeri'os milmala. This
is what it was both. Okay there wasn't a roof so the
אהל ohel because the word אהל ohel fundamentally speaks about like לאהל
על המשכן le'ohel al hamishkan speaks about the roof right that's the
word אהל ohel was about roofing over something. So that was a
curtain. Okay but the בית bayis is the surrounding
structure you know is the walls. Okay. ויריעות מלמעלה Viyeri'os milmala והיא
היתה מנוחה vehi haysa menucha that was the מנוחה menucha it was
a resting place it wasn't the נחלה nachala which is for all
permanent time because after that got destroyed במות were permissible and it
got moved again.
You know we recreate this in סוכות. Succos.
I was actually going to say that thank you for mentioning that.
Yeah the very fact that by your סוכה succah the הלכות halachos
of what defines it as a temporary dwelling and what you need
to make the סכך sechach you know grow from the ground etc.
all focus on the roof right? The actual structure of the walls
can actually be permanent you know so absolutely.
So you know maybe that evokes somewhat of a שילה Shilo? thing
but not a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash thing.
You mean because it's that sense of travel and impermanence but it's
also yeah it's a nice idea thinking about that. I mean most
people the סוכה succah even the walls are temporary. Right I understand.
No I mean these days you get like some pretty
strong I know I know these days yeah yeah you know I've
seen stuff like these major structures with wood and hammers and it's
like a real okay. Okay קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Now now we
get to the other thing that's distinctive about שילה Shilo although all
the קרבנות korbanot were brought because it was not you didn't have
a sense of ירושלים Yerushalayim a city you had to determine what
was the zone in which you could eat the קדשים קלים. kodashim
kalim. קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim which were in the you know were
in the sort of like the curtains the courtyard fine but קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim in ירושלים Yerushalayim you have a city that's around
it and that defines the next zone of the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay
what would it be by שילה? Shilo Now you could say how
about the city of שילה? Shilo You know why not say if
that's where the if that's where the temple is then the city
of שילה Shilo is like ירושלים Yerushalayim but interestingly again maybe because
it wasn't that permanent resting place that was not the הלכה and
maybe because there's no status to the city of שילה Shilo like
ירושלים Yerushalayim the weight of ירושלים Yerushalayim you know goes back historically
right there's no weight to שילה Shilo that goes back historically. So
therefore where you could eat the קדשים קלים kodashim kalim was not
about שילה Shilo. about the city of שילה Shilo it was about
the connection to the מקדש. Mikdash. So therefore you could eat it
from any place from which you could see the מקדש. Mikdash. And
the גמרא Gemara is going to say you could be in the
next tribe over you could be miles and miles away and if
you see the מקדש Mikdash because of your line of sight you're
on a mountain you can eat the קרבנות. korbanot, So it's really
not about the city of שילה Shilo. it's about the connection to
the מקדש Mikdash and where you see it.
Which is funny because you could be in the same place but
at the bottom of the mountain and like you can't.
Right yeah exactly because that's the point it's not about the geographical
city it's about in that sense of being in the environs and
being connected. Okay so מנא הני מילי Mina hani mili where's this
from? אמר רבי אושעיא דאמר קרא Amar Rabbi Oshaya damar kra the
verse says השמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך בכל מקום אשר תראה. Hishamer
lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha bechol makom asher tireh. Don't bring your sacrifices
wherever you see. This is about when the במות are forbidden. בכל
מקום אשר תראה אי אתה מעלה Bechol makom asher tireh i ata
ma'aleh you can't bring them wherever you see once there's a central
place like שילה. Shilo אבל אתה אוכל בכל מקום שאתה רואה. Aval
ata ochel bechol makom she'ata ro'eh. Okay but you can eat your
sacrifices wherever you see now the wherever you see in the פשט
pshat of the פסוק pasuk is anywhere you see fit. Okay but
here it's saying anywhere you see שילה Shilo? you can eat the
sacrifice. So the גמרא says אימא why don't I read it בכל
מקום שאתה רואה אי אתה מעלה bechol makom she'ata ro'eh i ata
ma'aleh you can't you can't offer them up on the altar to
on the fire wherever you see אבל אתה זובח בכל מקום שתראה
aval ata zove'ach bechol makom shetireh maybe you can sacrifice if you're
in sight of שילה. Shilo, How come you read it you can
eat if you're in sight of שילה Shilo. why not read that
you can sacrifice if you're in sight of שילה? Shilo אמר רבי
ינאי אמר קרא שם תעלה ושם תעשה Amar Rabbi Yannai amar kra
sham ta'aleh vesham ta'aseh because it says there in that central place
you should offer up and there you should do it. So the
same places that are so where you're limited to offer it up
is also where you're limited to sacrifice. So even though sacrifice sometimes
we are more expansive a non כהן Kohen can sacrifice, no sorry,
even when you're in שילה, Shilo, all of the עבודה Avodah has
to be in the מקדש Mikdash in שילה. Shilo. The more expansive
is not the עבודה Avodah but the place that you're eating it.
רב דימי בר רב חסדא אמר קרא. Rav Dimi Bar Rav Chisda
amar krah. So now we're going to have other verses that speak
to this more expansive sense of שילה Shilo. of where you can
be eating the קרבנות. korbanot Okay so the verse says, ולא תאנח
שילה, Velo te'anach Shilo, and there is the תאנח שילה. te'anach Shilo.
So if you look at the רש"י, Rashi, there's a great רש"י.
Rashi. רש"י Rashi says, חיפשתיו ולא מצאתיו. chipastiv velo metzativ. I have
looked through all of תנ"ך Tanach and I cannot find this verse
that the גמרא is quoting במקרא, bemikra, אבל מצאתי aval matzati I
have found a verse that is similar to it, because it says
ונסב הגבול מזרחה תאנת שלה. venasav hagvul mizrachah Ta'anach Shilo. That the
boundary sort of goes eastward towards שילה, Shilo this is about the
boundary of יוסף Yosef in יהושע. Okay, this is about... this is
about the... so anyway, so there's a verse that says תאנת שלה.
Ta'anach Shilo. What does תאנת שלה Ta'anach Shilo mean? The פשט peshat
probably is a name place. But the גמרא says מקום שכל הרואה
אותו מתאנח עליו. makom shekol haroeh oso mit'ane'ach alav. It is wherever
you sigh over שילה. Shilo. So you sort of see it in
a distance, okay, and because you remember like that, oh my gosh,
we could eat קרבנות like I guess this is after there's no
longer a מקדש mikdash in שילה. Shilo. You see the place and
it's in sight of שילה Shilo and you realize that you used
to be able to eat קרבנות here and you're no longer able
to eat קרבנות here. Anyway so it has that sense of that
even in a distance place, a place that's quite distant, you could
still have eaten the קרבנות, okay? So על אכילת קדשים al achilat
kodshim of שילה. Shilo רבי אבהו אמר קרא, Rabbi Abahu amar krah,
the verse says, בן פורת יוסף בן פורת עלי עין. ben porat
Yosef ben porat alei ayin. So we just said before, right, that
God, the tent that God had made in יוסף Yosef and in
אפרים, Ephraim, right, we quoted that verse a minute ago about שילה.
Shilo So now שילה Shilo. is in the section of אפרים, Ephraim,
the section of יוסף. Yosef. And it says by יוסף Yosef he
is a, you know, a fecundous, fruitful son, spreading out over the
עין ayin or whatever that means, or over the wellspring. So what
does that
mean? עין שלא רצתה ליהנות מדבר שאינו שלו. Ayin shelo ratztah lehannos
midavar she'eino shelo. The eye that did not want to benefit from
something that wasn't his. He did not want to have sex with
the wife of פוטיפר Potiphar even though she was seducing him. He
did not desire that which was not his, so he watched his
eye. תזכה ותאכלה כמלוא עיניה. Tizkeh vesochalah kemlo eineha. That eye is
rewarded that now, as far as the eye can see, it's able
to go ahead and to eat the sacrifices. So you know, the
eye and the seeing, right? So if you restrict your eye, you
know, your sense of not taking what's not yours, then you're rewarded
by the sense of all the eye can see. So because of
that, wherever you can see שילה Shilo from, you were able to
eat the sacrifices and connect to God in that way. רבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא אמר, Rabbi Yosi Be-Rabbi Chanina amar, he says, again the
same thing about יוסף, Yosef, except the פסוקים psukim in דברים Devarim
now: ורצון שכני סנה, uretzon shocheni sneh, the desire of the one
who dwells in the bush, presumably God. עין שלא רצתה ליהנות מדבר
שאינו שלו. Ayin shelo ratztah lehannos midavar she'eino shelo. So again, the
eye that did not want to benefit from something that it was
not... it did not deserve. תזכה ותאכלה בין השנואין. Tizkeh vesochalah bein
hasnu'in. So this is again שכני סנה, shocheni sneh, not reading סנה
sneh as the thornbush, but as the שנואין, snu'in, those that hate
it, right? Because we have that by יוסף, Yosef, the brothers hated
יוסף. Yosef. That's a verb that's actually used, right, וישנאו אותו. vayisnu
oso. So that means that you are rewarded that now somebody can
be in a different tribe, can be in the territory of a
different tribe, one of the other brothers' tribes who throughout your life,
you יוסף, Yosef, you know, felt the, you know, the sort of
the antagonism and the hatred, the animosity. Now you are going to
be so rewarded, you're going to stretch out that your power eventually
will be felt even in the territory of the other tribes. That
somebody could be sitting in יהודה, right, and eating קרבנות because of
their connection to שילה Shilo, because they're on a high place and
they can see שילה. Shilo And they can eat the sacrifices connecting
to, you know, the משכן Mishkan in שילה Shilo. because, you know,
even from... even being present in another tribe. That's how far you're
rewarded. Okay, now, תנא. Okay, so anyway, those are nice little מדרשי
midrashic points, but that's the idea, that you don't even have to
be geographically close, you just be able to have to be able
to see it. We taught in a ברייתא: baraita: רואה שאמרו, roeh
she'amru, when they said you're able to see it. Okay, רואה
כולו, roeh kullo,
you have to be able to see it all of it, it
sounds like, although the גמרא is going to talk about exactly whether
that means all of it. Okay, but the next line is: ולא
המפסיק בינו לבינו. velo hamafsik beino leveino. It's not if there's something
interrupting, which is basically means you could be a hundred feet away,
but there's an obstruction. So it has to be without an obstruction.
So, you know, that means it could be extremely far, but it...
and you could still eat, but it could be very close and
you can't eat because there's something obstructing your sight. So now the
גמרא is going to... אמר ליה רבי שמעון בן יקים לאלעזר *Amar
lei Rabbi Shimon ben Yakam l'Elazar*, אסברה לך *asberah lach*, let me
give you an example, a concrete example, כגון בית כנישתא דמעון *kegon
Beit Kenishta de-Ma'on*, like the synagogue of מעון *Ma'on*. If you're there,
maybe that was on a high place, they would build their synagogues
on high places, and even though that's far away, since you can
see שילה Shilo *Shilo*, you could... that's a place you could be
eating from. אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Pappa*: רואה שאמרו לא רואה
כולה *roeh she-amru lo roeh kullah*. And this is why the earlier
ברייתא *Baraita* there's a question about the גירסא *girsa*, because the earlier
one said you see the whole thing, and now the גמרא *Gemara*
is saying actually you don't have to see the whole thing. So
that's why there was a question of the גירסא *girsa*. לא רואה
כולה *lo roeh kullah*, you don't have to see the whole thing,
אלא רואה מקצתה *ela roeh miktzatah*. Even if you only see like
a little piece of שילה Shilo *Shilo*, that's okay. Now by the
way, I've been saying that what it means to see it, means
that you can see the משכן *Mishkan* wherever you are. But the
actual thing of seeing שילה Shilo. *Shilo* might sound like it means
that you can see the town of שילה Shilo *Shilo*. Okay, I'm
assuming it means that you can actually see
the משכן *Mishkan*, you can actually see where the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*
itself is built. But I do want to point out that the
simple meaning here is it says that you can actually see... it
sounds like it's saying you can see שילה Shilo. *Shilo* itself. Okay,
which then would be funny because a minute ago I was talking
about how, you know, there really wasn't a status to the town
of שילה Shilo, *Shilo* the way there was a status to ירושלים
Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. But if what connects you to the משכן *Mishkan* is
seeing the town of שילה Shilo, *Shilo*, not seeing the משכן *Mishkan*,
you know, then that is a little bit significant. It does give
like status to the actual town. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this. בעי רב פפא *Ba'ei Rav Pappa*. רב פפא *Rav
Pappa*, who liked asking these types of questions, asked the following question:
עומד ורואה יושב ואינו רואה מאי *omed v'roeh, yoshev v'eino roeh, mai*?
If when you're standing you can see it, but if you're sitting
you can't, okay, is that considered that you are in a place
where you can see it? Now you could ask the question... you
know, does that mean can I eat my קרבנות *korbanot* when I'm
sitting? Or, you know, can I eat them when I'm standing but
not when I'm sitting? Or should I say that no, you know,
because when I'm standing I can see it, I can even eat
it sitting? Or should I say the opposite? Since when I'm sitting
I can't see it, I can't even eat it when I'm standing?
You know, you don't know which way to go with that question,
right? Okay. בעי רבי ירמיה *Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmiah*. Now רבי ירמיה *Rabbi
Yirmiah* asked, רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiah* even more liked asking these types
of questions: עומד על גבי הנחל ורואה בתוך הנחל ואינו רואה מאי
*omed al gabei ha-nachal v'roeh, b'toch ha-nachal v'eino roeh, mai*? Let's say
you're by a wadi. You know, a wadi would be like a
deep crevice, right? So if you're at the top of the wadi,
you can see שילה Shilo *Shilo*. If you go into the wadi,
you can't. What's the story? Now I don't understand why that's such
a question. Fine, at the top of the wadi you can eat
it, at the bottom of the wadi you can't. But I don't
know, maybe he felt that conceptually we view that all as one
location, right? And therefore maybe you have to have one ruling for
both. Anyway, the גמרא *Gemara* says תיקו *teiku*, we don't know. יתיב
רב דימי *Yativ Rav Dimi*. When רב דימי *Rav Dimi* came from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*, הוא אמר רבי *hu amar Rabbi*,
he said in the name of רבי *Rabbi*: בשלושה מקומות שרתה שכינה
בישראל *B'shlosha mekomot sharta Shechinah b'Yisrael*. It dwelt in three places. Again,
this is the idea, right? That in שילה Shilo. *Shilo*, you know,
it's actually where like
the... the ארון Aron *Aron* was, and so on. So it dwelt
in three places: בשילה *b'Shilo*, בנוב וגבעון *b'Nov u'Givon*. Now בנוב וגבעון
*b'Nov u'Givon* is strange because בנוב וגבעון *b'Nov u'Givon* is what we're
going to see that was the period actually when the ארון Aron
*Aron* wasn't there. But he's still calling it a place of the
dwelling of the divine presence, which is fascinating because even though the
במה גדולה *bamah gedolah* was in נוב Nov *Nov* and גבעון Giv'on,
*Givon*, it wasn't where the ארון Aron *Aron* was. So that's strange
and the גמרא *Gemara* never fully unpacks that. Okay, ובית עולמים *u'Beit
Olamim*, and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. But his bigger
point was, these were the three major locations (or the four, נוב
Nov *Nov* and גבעון Giv'on? *Givon* are really two) locations from שילה
Shilo, *Shilo* onwards of where the מקדש *Mikdash* was. Right? שילה Shilo
*Shilo*, נוב Nov *Nov*, גבעון Givon. *Givon*, and the בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash*. And
here's
his חידוש *chiddush*: ובכולן לא שרתה אלא בחלקו של בנימין *u'v'chulan lo
sharta ela b'chelko shel Binyamin*. All those three were in the portion
of בנימין *Binyamin*. Now, if you might remember when we talked about
the מקדש *Mikdash*, we talked about how, you know, a piece of
the מזבח *mizbeach* was יהודה *Yehuda*, but basically it was בנימין *Binyamin*,
right? The יהודה *Yehuda* and בנימין *Binyamin* should be juxtaposed right along
the lines in the מקדש *Mikdash*. But now, to say that שילה
Shilo, *Shilo* is בנימין *Binyamin*, we just quoted a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
that says שילה Shilo? *Shilo* is יוסף *Yosef*. So he's claiming שילה
Shilo, *Shilo*, נוב Nov *Nov*, גבעון Givon *Givon*, and ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*
are all in בנימין *Binyamin*. So really? It sounded like a minute
ago we were saying it was יוסף *Yosef*. יוסף *Yosef*?
Isn't בנימין יוסף *Binyamin Yosef*? I mean...
no. No. I mean, it's that... it's his brother, it's that section
of the family, but it's not, it's a different tribe, right? So
I mean, so we said it was אפרים *Ephraim*, and here it's
saying בנימין *Binyamin*. So that's going to bother the גמרא *Gemara*. The
גמרא *Gemara* says שנאמר *she'ne-emar*, but anyway he bases this not on
פסוקים *pesukim* in יהושע *Yehoshua* that describe where things were, but based
on the following פסוק pasuk *pasuk*: חופף עליו כל היום *Chofef alav
kol hayom*. God hovers over בנימין *Binyamin* the entire day. כל חפיפה
לא תהא אלא בחלקו של בנימין *kol chafifah lo tehei ela b'chelko
shel Binyamin*. All of the places of God's hovering presence are always
within בנימין *Binyamin*. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute... כי
אזל אביי *Ki azal Abaye*, when אביי *Abaye* went, אמר קמיה דרב
יוסף *amar kamei d'Rav Yosef*, he said this teaching over in front
of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*. אמר *Amar*, so רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*
said: חד ברא הוה ליה לחיילי *chad bra hava leh l'Cheili*. חיילי
*Cheili* had one son, presumably חיילי *Cheili* was אביי *Abaye*'s father, okay.
He had one son, ולא מתקן *v'lo matkan*, and this one son
can't get things right. Okay. So meaning, what a silly thing for
you to say, אביי *Abaye*, even though אביי *Abaye* was just saying
it over. But he says you should have realized this is wrong.
Why? והכתיב
*V'haktiv*, the verse says: ויטוש משכן שילה Shilo *Vayintosh Mishkan Shilo*. abandon
the משכן *mishkan* of שילה *Shiloh*. וכתיב ve'chtiv, וימאס באהל יוסף ובשבט
אפרים לא בחר *Uch’tiv vayimas b’ohel Yosef uv’shevet Ephraim lo vachar*. It
makes it clear that it means he's abandoning his place in יוסף
*Yosef* and in אפרים *Ephraim*, not in בנימין *Binyamin*. שילה *Shiloh*'s in
יוסף *Yosef*. אמר רב אדא מאי קקשי ליה *Amar Rav Adda mai
kakasheilei*? Why was, why is, it's quite funny by the way, it's
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, it just occurs to me, who's taking offense
here? But anyway, why is רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* so upset that
ah, you know, this teaching of רב דימי *Rav Dimi* was it
was בנימין *Binyamin* and the פסוקים *pesukim* make it clear it's יוסף
*Yosef*? Well, we can solve that problem. How can we solve that
problem? מאי קקשי ליה *Mai kakasheilei*? Why is that difficult? דילמא שכינה
בחלקו בנימין וסנהדרין גדולה בחלק יוסף *Dilma shechina bechelko Binyamin vesanhedrin gedola
bechelek Yosef*? Maybe it was split just like by ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*.
You know, the שכינה *shechina* where is where the ארון Aron *aron*
was or maybe where the מזבח *mizbe'ach* was, that was בנימין *Binyamin*.
Okay? And יוסף *Yosef*'s portion went right up to that, you know,
included the place that the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* was. It's fascinating the גמרא
*Gemara* imagines the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* dwelt in שילה *Shiloh* as well, you
know, that they had a place in the מקדש *mikdash* in שילה
*Shiloh*. But whatever, maybe they juxtaposed, you know, just like it did
in the in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. All right. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, מידי דהוי אבית עולמים *Midei dahavei aveis olamim*. We find the
same thing like in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. שכינה בחלקו של
בנימין וסנהדרין בחלק יהודה *Shechina bechelko shel Binyamin vesanhedrin bechelek Yehuda*, and
the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* right right up to the up to the מזבח
*mizbe'ach* is the יהודה *Yehuda* section. So maybe that was the same
thing here with a split of יוסף *Yosef* and בנימין *Binyamin*. אמר
ליה הכי השתא *Amar leih hachi hashta*? What type of comparison is
that? התם מיקרב נחלות גבי הדדי *Hasam mikrav nachalot gabi hadadi*. There
יהודה *Yehuda* and בנימין *Binyamin* are juxtaposed, their portion. הכא מי מיקרבין
*Hacha mi mikravin*? So here since when are they juxtaposed? So if
you look at a tribe of, let me see if I can
pull one up, a tribe of the division of the שבטים *shevatim*.
Hold on.
See if I can quickly find one.
Okay, so,
I'm
pulling one up.
Okay, so here,
so
actually, see, it which is a funny question because if you look
at it, it actually is that I'm going to draw based
on this, this I just whatever got a map off of the
internet right now. But anyway, if you got something like this, right,
right like that, right? So you have like, you know, מנשה *Menashe*
is sort of like this,
something like this, well let me put this one down whatever. That's
like מנשה *Menashe*. Okay, this is אפרים *Ephraim*. אפרים
*Ephraim* and מנשה *Menashe*, I mean יוסף *Yosef* has a huge section
if you think about it, right? Anyway, here is בנימין *Binyamin*.
And here
is
like יהודה
*Yehuda* with שמעון *Shimon* somewhere in here.
Okay, so anyway, so if this is where ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* was
and that got split, the מקדש *mikdash* was right between בנימין *Binyamin*
and and יהודה *Yehuda*, now that we're saying that the שילה *Shiloh*
was in אפרים *Ephraim*, okay, but בנימין *Binyamin* also like the שכינה
*shechina* was in בנימין *Binyamin*, you could have had it right over
here. Okay, now I don't know if that's exactly where שילה *Shiloh*
is, let me see if שילה *Shiloh*'s on my map. No, so
it so in my map שילה *Shiloh* is over here, which I
assume is correct based on, you know, there's so much archaeology. Okay,
but in theory אפרים *Ephraim* and בנימין *Binyamin* are juxtaposed the same
way יהודה *Yehuda* is, and in theory you could imagine that it
could be split between בנימין *Binyamin* and אפרים *Ephraim* the same way
it was split between בנימין *Binyamin* and יהודה *Yehuda*. So that's the
גמרא *Gemara*'s question. הכי השתא התם מיקרב נחלות גבי הדדי *Hachi hashta
hasam mikrav nachalot gabi hadadi*. By יהודה *Yehuda* and בנימין *Binyamin* they
were juxtaposed, they were juxtaposed the the portion. הכא מי מיקרבין *Hacha
mi mikravin*? Since when here are they juxtaposed? The גמרא *Gemara* says,
הכי נמי מיקרבין *Hachi nami
mikravin*. So what do you mean? They are, they could be juxtaposed.
כדאמר רבי חמא ברבי חנינא *Kide'amar Rabbi Chama berabbi Chanina*: רצועה היוצאה
מחלקו של יהודה ונכנסה לחלקו של בנימין *Retzuah hayotza mechelko shel Yehuda
venichnasa lechelko shel Binyamin*. The same way יהודה *Yehuda* got a piece
of the מקדש *mikdash* because a little strip, you know, even if
יהודה *Yehuda*'s portion ended here and the מקדש *mikdash* was over here
a little strip entered in, okay, in order that they should have
a little a portion of the מקדש *mikdash*. So therefore, ובה היה
המזבח בנוי *Uvah hayah hamizbe'ach banuy*, and that's where the מזבח *mizbe'ach*
was. היה בנימין הצדיק מצטער עליה לבלעה *Hayah Binyamin hatzaddik mitztayer aleha
leval'ah*, בנימין *Binyamin* wanted to swallow it up. Okay, and that was
that whole מדרש *Midrash* right about which part of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*,
you know, was יהודה *Yehuda* and בנימין *Binyamin* and so on. Anyway,
so the גמרא *Gemara* says, הכי נמי רצועה היוצאה מחלקו של יוסף
לחלקו של בנימין *Hachi nami retzuah hayotza mechelko shel Yosef lechelko shel
Binyamin*. So here too. Now if you imagine it was right over
here it would be easy, but if you assume that שילה *Shiloh*
is here, the גמרא *Gemara* is still saying... Well actually you know
here the גמרא *Gemara* says it went from יוסף *Yosef* into בנימין
*Binyamin*. So that doesn't really work. You could say the opposite. You
could say בנימין *Binyamin* had a strip all the way up here
into אפרים *Efraim* because this is where שילה *Shiloh* is. But anyway
the גמרא *Gemara* is probably ignoring the fact that שילה *Shiloh* is
here. So it's saying okay so they are juxtaposed and you could
have had אפרים *Efraim* having a and mostly it's in בנימין *Binyamin*
and אפרים *Efraim* having a strip of land going in and having
a major section of the מקדש *Mikdash* which is situated in אפרים
*Efraim*. Okay והיינו דכתיב Dechtiv *v'hainu d'chtiv* יצא מחלקו של יוסף *yatzah
m'chelko shel Yosef* I'm sorry situated in בנימין *Binyamin*. So you could
imagine a strip going out from אפרים *Efraim* and going you could
imagine שילה *Shiloh* being in בנימין *Binyamin* and it's fundamentally in בנימין
*Binyamin* the same way the מקדש *Mikdash* was and a strip going
out from אפרים *Efraim* and getting a major portion of it. Okay
לחלקו של בנימין *l'chelko shel Binyamin* והיינו דכתיב dechtiv *v'hainu d'chtiv* and
that would be meant by the verse תאנת שלה *Te'anat Shiloh* the
sort of the the the moaning of שילה *Shiloh* or maybe it
means the extending of שילה *Shiloh*. Right? So here you know שילה
*Shiloh* is here and you would extend אפרים *Efraim* into שילה *Shiloh*
in order to get a portion of the you know of the
מקדש *Mikdash*. So again it doesn't really work once you realize that
שילה *Shiloh* is over here but the גמרא *Gemara* wants to imagine
the same way you had בנימין *Binyamin* and יהודה *Yehuda* juxtaposed with
ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* and the שכינה *Shechina* in בנימין *Binyamin* here although
שילה *Shiloh*'s in אפרים *Efraim* it wants to imagine that it was
fundamentally in בנימין *Binyamin* as well.
What's the significance of the contrast between יהודה *Yehuda* and אפרים *Efraim*
here in terms of sharing the space with בנימין *Binyamin*? Is there
any significance?
What do you mean the contrast? You mean the parallel? What do
you mean?
In other words in one case we're talking about יהודה *Yehuda* sharing
with בנימין
*Binyamin* and here we're talking about אפרים *Efraim*. Well you know I
mean it's like it's in general like right you know that I
mean in general the whole thing with you know who is sort
of the בכור *Bechor* and who has like the sense of leadership
and so on right it's the whole thing about בני יוסף *Bnei
Yosef* and בני יהודה *Bnei Yehuda* and you know בני רחל *Bnei
Rachel* and בני לאה *Bnei Leah* right so it's true also about
the kingship right that is the kingship from יהודה *Yehuda* right or
is the kingship שאול Shaul *Shaul* right was was from יוסף *Yosef*
right it was from אפרים *Efraim* so basically so by the מקדש
*Mikdash* as well in the early stages right it was more you
know sort of יוסף *Yosef* you know in terms of the kingship
and in terms of the מקדש *Mikdash* and so on you know
and later it sort of shifted both the you know the kingship
and the מקדש *Mikdash* to the יהודה *Yehuda section. Okay בנימין *Binyamin*
why בנימין *Binyamin* is sort of always right there in the middle
right that's an interesting idea that חופף עליו כל היום *chofef alav
kol hayom* that uniqueness of the divine presence sort of always be
sort of seen him as like this mediating factor between those two
I don't know but yeah but the shift the emphasis here of
like you know בני רחל *Bnei Rachel* and בני לאה *Bnei Leah*
right and somehow so that the fact that the מקדש *Mikdash* here
at least the sense is the מקדש *Mikdash* is shared between those
two major factions right בני מקדש *Bnei Mikdash* and here it's all
right here it's all within you know בני רחל *Bnei Rachel* right
אפרים *Efraim* and בנימין *Binyamin*. Okay yeah so the גמרא *Gemara* says
okay כתנאי
*k'tannai* this question of whether שילה *Shiloh* was in בנימין *Binyamin* or
not is a debate of תנאים *Tannaim*. חופף עליו *chofef alav* God's
presence hovers over זה מקדש ראשון *zeh Mikdash Rishon* that's the first
בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. כל היום *kol hayom* the entire day זה
מקדש שני *zeh Mikdash Sheini* the second בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. ובין
כתפיו שכן *uvein kteifav shachen* which is the third period אלו ימות
המשיח *eilu yemot hamashiach* the messianic period. So that means though that
God's presence in בנימין *Binyamin* was only in the מקדש *Mikdash* time
not in the שילה *Shiloh* time which is like the פשט *Pshat*
okay that the שילה *Shiloh* was not in בנימין *Binyamin*. רבי *Rabbi*
אומר *omer* רבי *Rabbi* says no חופף עליו *chofef alav* זה עולם
הזה *zeh olam hazeh* in this in in in you know in
normal recorded history God was always in בנימין *Binyamin*. So that's very
blanket so that would include even the period of שילה *Shiloh* claiming
that even even when the משכן *Mishkan* was in שילה *Shiloh* that's
where God's presence was so that שילה *Shiloh* is in בנימין *Binyamin*
to you know okay so זה עולם הזה *zeh olam hazeh* כל
היום *kol hayom* אלו ימות המשיח *eilu yemot hamashiach* messianic period. ובין
כתפיו שכן *uvein kteifav shachen* זה העולם הבא *zeh ha'olam habah* which
is fascinating. How is עולם הבא *Olam Haba* different than ימות המשיח
*Yemot HaMashiach*? The simple עולם הבא *Olam Haba* in the גמרא *Gemara*
does not mean after you die your soul goes to עולם הבא
*Olam Haba*. It means after the messianic period there will be a
new world on this planet and that's the future world on this
planet you know and that's the עולם הבא *Olam Haba* that comes
after the messianic period. Anyway so from רבי *Rabbi* you see it
says that God was always in בנימין *Binyamin* so presumably even when
it was in שילה *Shiloh* that was considered to be in בנימין
*Binyamin*. Okay תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan* now we're going to sort of
do a nice little history of the whole stages. ימי אהל מועד
שבמדבר *yemei ohel moed shebamidbar* the year the period of the אהל
מועד *Ohel Moed* in the in the מדבר *Midbar* was ארבעים שנה
חסר אחת *arbaim shana chaser achat* 39 years because they built it
and you know it was erected on the on ניסן *Nissan* the
ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* ניסן *Nissan* of the second year. So it
was 39 years. ימי אהל מועד שבגלגל *yemei ohel moed shebagilgal* then
it moved to גלגל *Gilgal* okay ארבע עשרה *arba esreh* was 14
years our whole discussion of גלגל *Gilgal*. זיין שכבשו וזיין שחלקו. Seven
that they conquered and in seven that they divided. Okay, the land.
ימי אהל מועד שבנוב וגבעון Yimei Ohel Moed shebeNov u'Giv'on and from
there it moved to נוב—well Nov actually no, from there it moved
to שילה, but we're discussing all the time around שילה in order
to figure out how long it was in שילה. Okay, so it
went from there to שילה and from שילה it went to נוב
Nov and גבעון. Givon So ימי אהל מועד שבנוב וגבעון, Yimei Ohel
Moed shebeNov u'Giv'on, the period it was in נוב Nov and גבעון
was חמישים ושבע, chamishim v'sheva, 57. So that allows us to figure
out how long it was in שילה. Why? Because the פסוק pasuk.
says that the בית המקדש was built 480 years since they left
מצרים. Mitzrayim. Okay, so here's here's יציאת מצרים, Yitziat Mitzrayim,
okay, and this says that this was built 480 years after. So
we're going to figure out how long it was in שילה by
taking out everything that is in שילה. Right? Isn't that how Michelangelo
said he carved the David? I just cut away everything that wasn't
David. Okay, so we're going to cut away everything that wasn't שילה,
okay? So you have 40 years here till they entered into ארץ
ישראל, right? And the משכן was starting on year two, so the
משכן was 39 of those, okay, but whatever. Okay, but anyway, 40
years here they entered into ארץ ישראל, okay. You had 14 years
of when it was in גלגל, okay. Then you had שילה, which
we'll figure out. Then you had נוב Nov and גבעון,
which is going to be 57. We're going to say how we
got all these things in a minute.
Okay, hold on. So this is 57, נוב and גבעון, okay. And
so here is then בית המקדש, 480. So 40 and 14 is
54. 54 and 57 is 111. So 480 minus 111,
let's see your math, is 369. Okay,
so here שילה is 369.
Okay,
so that's the next line. נשתיירו לשילה ג' מאות ושבעים חסר
אחת, Nishtayru le'Shilo gimel me'ot
v'shiv'im chaser achas,
370 minus 1, which is in other words 369. Okay, now, now
we're going to say how we know this. ימי אהל מועד שבמדבר
ארבעים חסר אחת מנא לן? Yimei Ohel Moed shebeMidbar arba'im chaser achas
minalan? How do you know it was 39 years in the מדבר?
דאמר מר שנה ראשונה עשה משה את המשכן, De'amar mar shana rishona
asa Moshe et haMishkan, the first year was being constructed. שנייה הוקם
המשכן, Shniya hukam haMishkan, which is an explicit פסוק that it was
put up on ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nisan of the second
year. Okay. ושלח משה מרגלים V'shalach Moshe meraglim and he sent the
מרגלים. meraglim. שבגלגל ארבע עשרה שנה, ShebeGilgal arba'esrei shana, how do you
know it was 14 years in גלגל? ארבע עשרה שכבשו ושבע שחלקו
מנא לן? Arba'esrei shekivshu v'sheva shechilku minalan? How do you know this?
דקאמר כלב, Dekamar Calev, because כלב Calev says at the end of
the period of conquering the land, okay, here's what כלב Calev says.
בן ארבעים שנה אנכי בשלוח משה עבד ה' מקדש ברנע לרגל את
הארץ, Ben arba'im shana anochi b'shloach Moshe eved Hashem miKadesh Barnea l'ragel
et ha'aretz, I was 40 years old when the מרגלים meraglim were
sent forth. ואשיב אותו דבר כאשר עם לבבי. Va'ashiv oto davar ka'asher
im levavi.
Okay, וכתיב, Vechtiv, so he was 40 when the מרגלים meraglim were
sent forth, and it says ועתה הנה אנכי היום בן חמש ושמונים
שנה, ve'ata hinei anochi hayom ben chamish v'shmonim shana, I'm 85 now.
Okay. כי עברו ליה ירדן בר כמה
הוה? Ki abru lei Yarden bar kama hava? So he was 40
when the מרגלים meraglim were sent forth, how old was he when
they crossed over the ירדן Yarden when they conquered the land? בר
שבעין ותמניא, Bar shiv'im u'tmanya, 78, because the מרגלים meraglim were sent
forth in year two. So he was 78. So he was 78
when they crossed over the ירדן and now he's 85 that they
finished conquering the land. דקאמר בן חמש ושמונים שנה, Dekamar ben chamish
v'shmonim shana, so he says now I'm 85. הרי שבע שכבשו, Harei
sheva shekivshu, so we see it took seven years to conquer the
land. גמרא וסברא, G'mara v'savar, and so how do we know though
that it took seven years to divide? Because it was afterwards divided
that it says that they sort of moved to, you know, to
שילה. So how do you know though it took seven years to
divide? ושבע שחלקו מנא לן? V'sheva shechilku minalan? How do you know
it took seven years to divide? איבעית אימא מדשבע שכבשו שבע נמי
שחלקו. Iba'it eima mide'sheva shekivshu sheva nam shechilku. Well, since it took
seven years to conquer, it took seven years to divide. As רש"י
Rashi says סברא בעלמא היא, sevara be'alma hi, which means yeah, that's
just some hypothesis or whatever. You know, סברא בעלמא sevara be'alma is
not like it says who knows why. Like, really? Because it took
seven to conquer, it should take seven to divide? Anyway, איבעית אימא,
iba'it eima, if you want I can tell you משכחת לה בארבע
עשרה שנה אחר שהוכתה העיר. mishkachat lah b'arba'esrei shana achar shehukta ha'ir.
So this is a complicated math where יחזקאל Yechezkel says in 14
years after ירושלים was destroyed. Anyway, it's a whole complicated computation about
how many שמיטהs Shemitta and יובלs Yovel they had in the land
that would make the calendar fall out in a certain way and
it depends on assuming that they didn't conquer the land, that they
didn't sort of divide the land for the first 14 years, that
because you only start the process of counting יובל Yovel when every
tribe is in its right location. So therefore based on various other
computations, we know that they only would have started the שמיטה, Shemitta,
like the normal שמיטה, Shemitta, יובל Yovel process, you know, counting the
יובלs Yovel or whatever, by year 14. Okay, so you'll just have
to trust me on this one. So with that, how we know
14 years. So now what we're left with is how do you
know 57 years of נוב and גבעון? So let's just finish up
with that for today.
אהל מועד שבנוב וגבעון חמישים ושבע. Ohel Moed shebeNov u'Giv'on chamishim v'sheva.
מנלן, minalan, where do you know this from?
דכתיב ויהי כהזכירו את ארון האלהים, Vayehi ke-hazkiro et aron ha-elokim, it
was when he remembered, this is by
עלי, Eli, that the ארון Aron of God had been taken captive
by the פלשתים, Plishtim he fell backwards and he died. ותנא Vetana
כשמת עלי הכהן חרב שילה. Keshemet Eli HaKohen charav Shilo. So here
the ארון was captive, was taken captive, so
here
the ארון is taken captive,
עלי Eli dies. That happens and that’s the period of שילה, חרב
שילה. Charav Shilo.
ובאו לנוב Uva'u leNov and they moved
the operation to נוב without the ארון. כשמת שמואל הרמתי, Keshemet Shmuel
HaRamati, now when שמואל Shmuel died, חרב נוב, Charav Nov, then they—now
you might remember שאול Shaul comes in and he destroys נוב the
city of כהנים Kohanim and
that’s how we know that the מקדש was in נוב because of
פסוקים in that discussion. Okay, so here that it was destroyed, ובאו
לגבעון Uva'u leGivon and they came to גבעון. וכתיב, vechtiv, okay, ויהי
מיום שבת הארון בקרית יערים Vayehi miyom shevet ha-aron beKiryat Ye'arim from
the days that the ארון was in the קרית יערים Kiryat Ye'arim
וירבו הימים ויהיו עשרים שנה, Vayirbu hayamim vayihyu esrim shana, it was
20 years. So we really didn't need the whole discussion
about when did it move from נוב to גבעון and so on,
but the key of knowing the total years is based on this
פסוק. It’s based on the idea that it says that the
ארון was retrieved 20 years later, okay?
So it was 20 years from the day that it was returned,
okay? So from being taken captive to being returned is 20 years.
וינהו כל בית ישראל אחרי ה', Vaye-nahu kol beit Yisrael acharei Hashem,
they longed after God. Now הני עשרים שנה, hanei esrim shana, those
20 years, עשר שנה שמלך שמואל בעצמו eser shana shemalach Shmuel be'atzmo
ושנה שמלך שמואל ושאול ushana shemalach Shmuel veShaul ושתיים שמלך שאול ushtayim
shemalach Shaul ושבע דדוד, vesheva deDavid, okay? So here עלי Eli dies,
okay? So עלי Eli dies here, okay? That’s when שמואל Shmuel takes
over, okay? So now you have 20 years until the ארון is
returned. ארון returned.
Rabbi, they suggest
that
it was within months
that the פלשתים actually
returned—oh, am I saying it wrong?
But it’s not in the text, it’s in their note here.
That’s what they suggest, I don’t
know.
Chapter 6 of... No, no, no, you’re right, you’re right, you’re right,
I’m sorry, I got confused. You’re right. It was returned right away,
you’re right, I’m sorry. It was returned right away and it stayed
in קרית יערים Kiryat Ye'arim for 20 years. Yeah, yeah, yeah, I’m
sorry, I got confused. So okay, so right. Okay, so it was
taken captive and it was sort of then it was returned. Thank
you, okay, and it was in קרית יערים Kiryat Ye'arim
for
years, okay? And then, okay, and then so
that’s—so okay.
So now שמואל Shmuel had 10 years.
Okay, where were we? Okay,
עשר שנה מלך שמואל בעצמו eser shana malach Shmuel be'atzmo ושנה שמלך
שמואל ושאול, ushana shemalach Shmuel veShaul, okay, then you had
שאול—it’s Shaul funny that they say שמואל Shmuel was king, okay, but
I guess he was the political authority also. Then you had שאול
Shaul, coming in, right, and he anoints שאול, Shaul okay, ושנה שמלך
שמואל ושאול ushana shemalach Shmuel veShaul and they sort of overlapped, and
then he dies, okay? And so שאול Shaul has one year, then
שמואל Shmuel dies, and then שאול Shaul's has another two years, okay?
So שמואל Shmuel dies here,
okay, and then he has another, and then שאול's Shaul whole kingship
ends after then, and then you have seven years of דוד David
in חברון Hevron before he was מלך melech in ירושלים. So those
20 years are in—it says in the verse it’s 20 years in
קרית יערים, Kiryat Ye'arim, but we're breaking it up this way, okay,
between שמואל Shmuel and שאול Shaul, and דוד. David. Those are the
20 years in קרית יערים. Kiryat Ye'arim. Where are you going to
get the extra 37 years? Because what happened after the ארון was
there for 20 years? So after the ארון was in קרית יערים
Kiryat Ye'arim for 20 years, it says... Okay,
ושבע דדוד, vesheva deDavid, דכתיב והימים אשר מלך דוד על ישראל ארבעים
שנה, ve-hayamim asher malach David al Yisrael arbaim shana, it was 40
years. בחברון מלך שבע שנים, be-Hevron malach sheva shanim, okay, so in
חברון Hevron it was 7, so what was the remainder of דוד's
David's rule?
33 years, right?
Right? That’s דוד David in ירושלים because דוד David was 40 years
total. 7 in חברון. Hevron. Okay, so now you have from נוב
and גבעון were 53 years: 20 years, the first 20, then דוד
David is king of ירושלים another 33, 53 years. And now שלמה
Shlomo is king. But שלמה Shlomo doesn't build it in year 1,
שלמה Shlomo builds it
in year 4. וכתיב, ובשלמה כתיב ויחל לבנות בשנת ארבע למלכותו. u-veShlomo
chtiv vayachel livnot bishnat arba lemalchuto. Okay,
so therefore you get 57, all right? You've got, you got basically,
you know, if you want to do it this way, you have
40 of דוד, David, okay, of the entire thing of דוד, David,
you've got 13 of שמואל Shmuel and שאול, and you have four
of שלמה Shlomo before it got built. So you have 57, okay,
from the time it was there, okay, so that makes 57, so
then ואישתייר ליה שלש מאות ושבעים חסר אחת, v'ishtayer leih shlosh me'os
v'shivim chasar achas, so that's how you know that it was in
שילה for 369 years. And the point being that was a heck
of a lot long time. Like, you know, we always think, yeah,
שילה, who even thinks about שילה? But it wasn't so much longer
in ירושלים than it was in שילה, right? In ירושלים it was
420 and in שילה it was 370, right? So it's like a
difference of 50 years, right? Okay, so that's how we get that
and we'll end with this for today.